Guide to the Clyde W. Deal Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Clyde W. Deal papers
1934-1978
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
1596
1596-006
Deal, Clyde W.
2.83 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, tape recorded interviews and transcripts, photographs, newsletters and reports relating to his activities as founder of the Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific and Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service
Clyde Deal was a founder, president and business manager of the Ferryboatmen's Union of California, later the Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, from 1918 to 1941. He joined the U.S. Conciliation Service in 1941 as a commissioner and served until 1945. For two years he was labor counselor in charge of labor negotions for the "Atlanta Journal." He rejoined the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service from 1948 to 1958. From 1958 to 1969, he was an arbitrator in labor disputes in California and Oregon. From 1965 to 1969, he was a labor consultant at the Tongue Point Job Corps Center in Oregon.
Correspondence, speeches and writings (including an autobiography); tape recorded interviews and transcripts, photographs, newsletters, reports 1934-1973 relating to Deal's personal life and activities as founder of the Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific; correspondence, mediation files, agreements and reports, 1939-1978, relating to Deal's work for the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service.
Open to all users.
Donated by Clyde W. Deal, 10/20/1970, 3/29/71, 4/16/71, 4/1974; by Dorothy Deal, 4/6/79; by Merle Adlum, 9/11/84. Transferred from Merle Adlum papers.
Inventory/container list available in Special Collections.
Deal, Clyde W.$vArchives; Bridges, Harry,$d1901-1990; Casey, Michael; Curran, Joseph; Grange, David; Peabody, Alex M.; Pegg, Ernest; Scharrenberg, Paul; Fox, John M.,$d1902-1978; Morse, Wayne L.$q(Wayne Lyman),$d1900-1974; Steelman, John R.; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Black Ball Line (Firm)$vArchives; Communist Party of the United States of America; Ferryboatmen's Union of California; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; International Longshoremen's Association; Maritime Federation of the Pacific Coast; National Maritime Union of America; International Seamen's Union; Southern Pacific Company; Inland Boatmen's Union of the Pacific; Tongue Point Job Corps Center (Astoria, Or.); United States. Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; California; Oregon; Oral Histories; Sound Recordings; Photographs
- Personal Papers
  - Biographical Features, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Family History, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - General Correspondence
    - Morse, Wayne, 1946 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Roberts, Oral, 1973 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Steelman, John R., 1968 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1934-77 (Box-folder 1/4-11)
  - Interview Transcripts
    - Clyde W. Deal on the Origin and Early History of the Inlandboatmen's Union's of the Pacific--by Vernon Steadman, 1955 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - by Richard Berner, 3/27/71 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - by Karyl Winn (see also Tape Recorded Interview), 4/16/71 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Tape Recorded Interviews (6) (Box-folder 4)
    - Tape I--by Karyl Winn, 10/20/70
      Describes negotiations with the Southern Railroad Company for a dismissal wage. Also discussed is the San Francisco General Strike of 1934 and Harry Bridges. Michael Casey of the Teamsters Union is also mentioned.
    - Tape II--by Karyl Winn, 10/20/70
      Includes Mr. Deal's views on the method of a labor leader. He also discusses the International Seamen's Union (AFL) and the National Maritime Union, with comments on Joe Curran and David Cerange. Communists in labor organizations is also one of the topics.
    - Tape III--by Karyl Winn, 10/20/70
      Early days of the Ferry-boatmen's Union of San Francisco. Organizing of the Maritime Federation of the Pacific.
    - Tape V--by Karyl Winn--, 04/16/71
      A synopsis of Deal's activities from 1918 to 1971. The organizing of the Maritime Federation of the Pacific.
    - Tape V Addition, 4/16/71
      Discussion of Teamsters Union's relationship to Inlandboatmen's Union. Speaks of John O' Connell and Michael Casey of Teamsters Union, and of Captain John Fox.
    - Two Taped Interviews by Matt Meekam, undated
  - Speeches And Writings
    - Book: The World of Work, The Tide Turns, and Teeter Totter (autobiography), undated (Box-folder 1/15-29)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 1/30-31 to 2/5)
  - Speeches And Writings--of Others (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Audio Cassettes Of Deal's Dictation (24), undated (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Drawings, undated (Box-folder 2/7-8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Statistics, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Conference And Convention Files--congress Of Industrial Organizations, 1940 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Blueprints--daisy Street, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Subject Series
    - Alaska Oil, undated (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Application to National Mediation Board, 1940, 47 (Box-folder 2/17)
- Inlandboatmen's Union Of The Pacific (IBU)
  - Biographical/historical Features, undated (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Constitution And Bylaws, undated (Box-folder 2/19)
  - General Correspondence (incl. John M. Fox), 1939-73 (Box-folder 2/20-24)
  - Speeches And Writings
    - A Personal History of the IBU--by Deal., 1975 (Box-folder 2/25)
      Featured in September, October, November, and December 1971 issues of the Inlandboatman of the Pacific Newsletter
    - Miscellaneous, 1967, undated (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Newsletter, 1968-73 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Legal Documents, undated (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Union Agreements, 1963-73 (Box-folder 2/29)
- U.S. Federal Mediation And Conciliation Service (U.S. Conciliation Service)
  - General Correspondence
    - Morse, Wayne, 1940-74 (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Steelman, John R., 1940-61 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - Letters of Commendation, 1940-54 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-71 (Box-folder 2/33-38)
  - Arbitration Files
    - Textile Workers of America, United. Local 2207 and North American Rayon Corporation, 1943 (Box-folder 2/39)
    - Atlanta Journal and Typographical Union,International. No. 48, 1946 (Box-folder 2/40)
    - Food Employers, Inc. vs. Food and Drug Clerks Union. Local 1092, 1958 (Box-folder 2/41)
    - Grain Millers, American Federation. Local 61 vs. Oregon Egg Producers, 1959 (Box-folder 2/42)
    - Boilermakers, Iron Shipbuilders, Blacksmiths, Forgersand Helpers, International Brotherhood. Local No. 72 and Hod Carriers, Building and Common Laborers of America, International Brotherhood. No. 320, 1960 (Box-folder 2/43)
    - Iron Fireman Manufacturing Company and Machinists, International Association. Lodge 63, 1961 (Box-folder 2/44)
    - Johnson Mat and Electrotype Company and Stereotypers and Electrotypers Union of North America (AFL-CIO), International. No. 29, 1961 (Box-folder 2/45)
    - Columbia Basin River Operators and Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, Columbia River Division, 1965 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Columbia River Towboat Association (Willamette Tug and Barge Co.) vs. Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific. Columbia River Division, 1965 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Columbia River Towboat Association vs. Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, 1966 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Oregon. School District UH2 and Directors Board and Teachers Association, Sandy Union High School, 1972 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Arbitration Instructional Material, undated (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Agreements, 1959-62 (Box-folder 3/6-7)
  - Application Forms, 1939 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Reports, 1950-52 (Box-folder 3/9-10)
  - Speeches And Writings, 1949-53 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Newsletters, 1958-78 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Publication--handbook Of Federal Labor Legislation Bulletin No. 39, 1941 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Subject Series--compensation Award, 1959-71 (Box-folder 3/15)
- Oregon. University. Tongue Point Job Corps Center
  - General Correspondence
    - Morse, Wayne, 1965-68 (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-69 (Box-folder 3/17)